http://amyxlu.github.io github.com/amyxlu

I am a graduate student at the University of Toronto/Vector Institute for AI. I am interested in **developing** biologically-principled machine learning methods, with an emphasis on self-supervised representation learning, generalizability, and biological interpretability. I also serve on Research to the People, which organizes research collaborations of genomics/ML researchers for patients of understudied diseases.

# **EDUCATION**

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

Bachelors of Science, Honours Science, Bioinformatics Option

2014 - 2018

University of Toronto, Vector Institute

Toronto, Canada

Master's in Computer Science

2019 - 2020

### EXPERIENCE

Stanford University

Palo Alto, USA

Visiting Student Researcher — Domain Adaptation in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Anshul Kundaje

2019 - 2019

• **Domain adaptation, ChIP-seq data, interpretability:** Using domain adaptation methods to improve transcription factor binding prediction when evaluating for a different cell line.

# University of Toronto/Vector Institute

Toronto, Canada

Masters Student — Representation learning in genomics, Dr. Alan Moses & Dr. Marzyeh Ghassemi

2019 - 2020

- Self-supervised learning, protein representation learning: Applied methods in NLP and mutual information maximization to learn self-supervised representations of protein sequences.
- Generalizability, computer vision: Benchmarked self-supervised computer vision methods in a microscopy image dataset with covariate shift to highlight generalization failures in machine learning. (NeurIPS 2019)
- Algorithmic fairness, clinical decision support: Quantitative and qualitative evaluation of bias in contextual word embeddings on clinical notes; fairness definitions for multi-group settings (Spotlight, ACM CHIL 2020)

#### Harvard Medical School/Boston Children's Hospital

Boston, USA

Research Intern — Machine Learning in Clinical Genomics, Dr. Piotr Sliz

2018 - 2019

- Genotype-phenotype studies, clinical interpretability: Understanding disease genotype-phenotype relationships using machine learning models. Interpreted important model features to seek novel disease-associated variants from whole exome (WES) data.
- Variant filtering, pathway analyses: Applied standard filtering pipelines for false-positive variants. Explored classification from pathway- and variant-level features.
- Machine learning, dimensionality reduction: Explored methods for capturing epistatic non-linearities and statistical dimensionality reduction.

### University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

Undergraduate Thesis Student — Deep Learning in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Andrew Doxey

2017 - 2018

- Chromatin accessibility prediction, interpretability: Trained a convolutional neural network to classify ATAC-seq accessible regions; reconstructed first-layer features as a position-weighted matrix (PWM) with statistical matches in JASPAR, a database of known motifs.
- Phylogenetics, metagenomic data mining: Used various bioinformatics pipeline tools (HMMER, BLAST, etc.) to understand biochemical properties of potentially uncharacterized toxins in metagenomic data.

# École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

Research Intern — Molecular Dynamics Simulations, Dr. Matteo Dal Parero

2017

• Molecular dynamics: Used molecular dynamics (MD) and GROMACS to simulate enzyme-membrane mechanisms of bacterial "superbugs"

## University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

 $Research\ Intern\ --\ Data\ Visualization\ in\ Pharmacoepidemiology,\ Dr.\ Suzanne\ Cadarette$ 

2015 - 2017

• Data visualization, pharmacoepidemiology: Analysis and visualization of the social diffusion of methodological innovation in pharmacoepidemiology.

- NSERC Postgraduate Scholarships Doctoral program (PGS D) Award [Declined]: Federal doctoral scholarship, selected in the Committee for Computing Sciences (\$63,000).
- Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarships Master's (CGS M) Award: Federal research grant (\$17,500).
- NSERC Michael Smith Foreign Supplement: "Supports high-calibre Canadian graduate students in pursuing research abroad" (\$6,000).
- Scholarship of Excellence in Research: Sponsors students for research internship at EPFL (CHF 4,500).
- University of Waterloo: Various entrance awards totaling \$6,000.
- Royal Conservatory of Music (RCM): ARCT Performer's Diploma in Piano.

#### Publications and Conference Proceedings

- **Preprint:** Lu AX, Zhang H, Ghassemi M, Moses AM. Self-Supervised Contrastive Learning of Protein Representations By Mutual Information Maximization. *bioRxiv*.
- Accepted: Zhang H\*, Lu AX\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Spotlight Talk, ACM Conference on Health, Inference, and Learning (CHIL) 2020. \*Equal contribution.
- Published: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Schormann W, Ghassemi M, Andrews DW, Moses AM. The Cells Out of Sample (COOS) dataset and benchmarks for measuring out-of-sample generalization of image classifiers. *Poster, Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2019.*
- Presented: Moses A, Lu AX, Lu AXP, Ghassemi M. Transfer Learning vs. Batch Effects: what can we expect from neural networks in computational biology? *Poster, Machine Learning for Computational Biology (MLCB)* 2019.
- Published: Ban J, Tadrous M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Cadarette SM. Diffusion of indirect comparison meta-analytic methods to study drugs: a systematic review and co-authorship network analysis. *BMJ Open*.

## Workshop Papers and Posters

- Presented: Lu AX\*, Zhang H\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Poster, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health. \*Equal contribution.
- Presented: Zhang H\*, Lu AX\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Extended Abstract, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Machine Learning for Healthcare. \*Equal contribution.
- Presented: Abdalla M, Zhang H, Lu AX, Chen I, Ghassemi M. Quantifying Fairness in a Multi-Group Setting and its Impact in the Clinical Setting. *Poster, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. Paired Cell Inpainting: A Multiple-Instance Extension of Self-Supervised Learning for Bioimage Analysis. *Poster, ICML 2019 Workshop on Self-Supervised Learning.*
- Presented: Lu AX, Rockowitz S, Poduri A, Sliz P. From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. Lightning Talk/Poster, Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019.
- Submitted: Lu AX, Tam ES. Effect of prophylactic brimonidine on subconjunctival hemorrhage in laser-assisted cataract surgery. *Poster Abstract*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Consiglio GP, Cadarette SM. Dynamic Visualization in Co-Authorship Network Analysis. *Poster, Leslie Dan Faculty of Pharmacy Undergraduate Research Symposium.*

## SERVICE AND ACTIVITIES

- Research to the People (formerly SVAI): Core Team of Research to the People, a non-profit connecting patients of rare genomic diseases to the medical/AI research community and industry partners through collaborative research initiatives.
- Residence Don: Organized events and established rapport with diverse students. Responded to mental health and conduct crises. Leader for the Velocity Residence, a spin-off for the Velocity start-up incubator.
- Tosamaganga Hospital, Tanzania: Supported operations at a rural Tanzanian hospital and shadowed surgical procedures. Expenses were covered by scholarships, fundraising, and part-time tutoring.

# Teaching

- Teaching Assistant, Genetics: Taught weekly tutorial lectures for BIOL 239 at the University of Waterloo.
- Piano, music theory: Taught piano performance (up to RCM 7), ear training, RCM music history, and RCM Intermediate Rudiments.
- Tutoring: Tutor for IB Math, Biology, and Chemistry.

# Talks

- Vector NLP Talks: Quantifying and Removing Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Co-presenter.
- Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019: From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. *Lightning talk*.